[{"question":"The Governor of a state is","choices":["Directly elected by the people","Elected by the state legislature","Appointed by the President","Appointed by the parliament"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"The Governor Powers do not include","choices":["Legislative powers","Military powers","Pardoning powers","Emergency powers"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"The Governor of a state is responsible for his actions to","choices":["The state legislative assembly","The president","The prime minister","The chief justice of the high court"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"State Governors are","choices":["Instruments of control of the centre over the state","Nominees of the chief minister","Elected by the Rajya sabha","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Ordinances issued by a state governor are subject to approval of","choices":["The president of India","Chief Minister of the state","Union parliament","State legislative concerned"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"Who, among the following, is not appointed by the Governor","choices":["Chief Minister","High Court judges","Members of the State Public Service Commission","Advocate General"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Legislative council is","choices":["Dissolved after 6 years","Dissolved after 5 years","Dissolved after 3 years","Not dissolved"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"A High Court Judge retires at the age of","choices":["65","63","60","62"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"Constitution empowers state governments to make special law for","choices":["Women and children","Workers working in the mines","Farmers","Unemployed youths"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"President rule is imposed in a state","choices":["When there is no clear majority","When state legislative passes a resolution to that effect","When there is difference of opinion between the Governor and the Chief Minister.","When the state government doesnt follow the direction given by the Prime Minister."],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"This is not the power of the chief minister","choices":["Formation of government","Control over minister","Chief advisor to the governor","Control over state judiciary"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"The minimum age for a person to be appointed as the governor of a state is","choices":["35","40","30","25"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"By convention, the Governor of a state generally belongs to","choices":["The same state","Some other state","The I.A.S. cadre","The same zone"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Who among the following holds office during the pleasure of the president?","choices":["Governor","Election Commissioner","Prime minister","Speaker of the loksabha"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The executive of the state government comprises the","choices":["President, Governor and the Chief Minister","Governor and the Chief Minister","Governor and the council of ministers","Chief Minister and his council of ministers"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Suffrage means","choices":["The right to suffer","The right of the citizen to expose the suffering of others","The right to vote","None of these"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Which of the following subjects may never be discussed in a state legislature","choices":["Conduct of a high court judge","Conduct of a marshal of the house","Items of the charged expenditure in the budget","Conduct of the Governor"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Who, among the following, can remove a chief minister from office?","choices":["State legislative assembly","Governor","President","Supreme court of India"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Election to a state legislature is conducted by the","choices":["State Governor","Chief Minister","Chief Secretary of the state","Election commission"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"When a state assembly is dissolved, the law making power for the state concerned rests with the","choices":["State Governor","Union Parliament","President of India","Chief Justice of India"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"The Chief Minister remains in power as long as he enjoys the confidence of the","choices":["Prime minister","Governor","State legislative assembly","people of the state"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Members of the council of ministers are appointed by","choices":["Chief Minister","Governor","Governor on the advice of the chief minister","State legislative assembly"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"A joint sitting of the Vidhana  Sabha and vidhana parishat of a state is presided over by the","choices":["Governor of the state","Chief minister","Chairman of the vidhana parishad","Speaker of the vidhana sabha"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The authority to dissolve a state legislative assembly is vested in the","choices":["Chief minister of a state"," Speaker of the state assembly","President of India","State governor"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"A few members of the legislative council are nominated by the","choices":["Chief minister","Governor of the state","Chairman of the legislative council","President of India"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Total members in the Legislative Council should not be less than","choices":["250","80","20","40"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"Governor will act as per the advice of the council of Ministers while","choices":["Giving assent to a bill","Dissolving the Legislative Assembly","Recommending Presidents Rule","Appointing the advocate General"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"The number of ministers, including the chief minister, in a state shall no be less than","choices":["15","12","10","5"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"The number of ministers including the chief minister shall not exceed____ of the total number of M.L.A.s","choices":["25%","30%","15%","20%"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"The Chief Minister of state is","choices":["Elected directly by the people","Selected by the President of India","Selected by hid party President","Elected by the Members of the Legislative Assembly"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"The Chief Minister is answerable for his acts of omission and commission to","choices":["The People","His party","Legislative Assembly","Investigation"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Budget of a State Government is based on","choices":["The vision of the council of Ministers","The preparation of the official of the state","The direction of the central Government","The direction of World Trade Organization"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The position of the chief minister in council of ministers is","choices":["the first among equal","the supreme commander","the virtual dictator","no difference at all with regard to position & status"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"To become a judge of the High Court one must be a practicing advocate of the High Court for at least","choices":["years","10 years","15 years","5 years"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"The judges of a High Court are","choices":["Liable to be transferred","Not liable to be transferred","Liable to be transferred once in 2 years","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The Chief Justice of a High Court gets a salary of","choices":["Rs. 56,000","Rs. 90,000","Rs. 75,000","Rs. 80,000"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"High Courts have original jurisdiction in","choices":["Admirality","Civil matters","Criminal matters","Matters not related will or divorce"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"High courts have appellate jurisdiction in","choices":["Civil matters","Criminal matters","Both criminal and civil matters","Constitutional matters"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"The decision of a High Court over rules the decision of","choices":["all other lower courts","is not binding on all other lower courts","it just a matter of reference to lower courts","none of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Public interest litigation can be entertained by a High court whenever","choices":["the public is irresponsible","the public neglect the Governments interests","the public interest is undermined","the public interest becomes personal interest of the high court"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"The high court has","choices":["The power of superintendence over all other lower courts","The power to create lower courts","The power to disengage the business of a lower court","The power to dissolve all or any lower court"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Judicial activism is","choices":["for the protection of the Rights of the citizens","for curtailment of the power of the Government","for the curtailment of active organization","for the follow up of the courts directions"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The independence of judiciary is necessary","choices":["effectively act as a guardian of peoples rights","to curb the powers of the Executive","to discipline the behaviour of the legislature","to encourage the media to counter the wrong decisions of the government"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The Judiciary is","choices":["A part of the Government","Nothing to do with the Government","Independent of Government","Against the Government"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The judiciary is provided by","choices":["The Constitution","The people","The Government","United Nations Organisation"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The best test of excellence of Government is the efficiency of its executive","choices":["The efficiency of its executive","The efficiency of its legislative","The efficiency of its Judicial system","All of these"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"The Judges of the High Court are","choices":["Appointed by the Chief Minister","Appointed by the Speaker of the Vidhana Sabha","Appointed by the President of India","Appointed by the Governor"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Judicial Review means","choices":["Reviewing the laws passed by the legislature","Examining the actions of the Executive","Scrutinizing the lower courts order","Supervising the implementation of the D.P.S.P"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The Supreme Court has the Power to","choices":["Create High Courts","Create the Whole Judicial system","Supervise and control the High Court","None of these"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"To become a chief minister of a state one must have attained the age of","choices":["25 years","30 years","35 years","40 years"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The list of SCs & STs is drawn by","choices":["Governor","President","Prime Minister","None of these"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"There can be reservation of seats in Lok Sabha & State Legislative Assemblies for SCs amd STs is contained in","choices":["Article 352, 360","Article 356, 359","Article 330, 332","None of these"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Article 243 (D) & 243 (T) provides for reservation of seats for SCs and STS in","choices":["Lok Sabha","Rajya Sabha","Panchayat Raj","Vidhana Sabha"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Under Article 338____ can be established for the SCs and STs","choices":["National Commission","Human Rights courts","Civil Courts","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"National Commission for SCs & STs shall have all the power of a","choices":["High Court","Supreme Court","Civil Court","Criminal Court"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Special Provisions for Scs and Sts are also contained in","choices":["Part I & II of the constitution","Part III & IV of the constitution","Part X of the constitution","Part of XVI of the constitution"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"___ Provides for grants-in-aid to the state for promoting the welfare of the SCs & STs","choices":["Article 280","Article 275","Article 249","Article 300"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"The legally permissible age for marriage of a boy & girl is","choices":["21 & 18 years","16 & 18 years","25 & 23 years","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Practices derogatory to use status of women in renounced under","choices":["Article 51 A (e)","Article 32","Article 50","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Right to education has been guaranteed to children between the age of","choices":["6-14 years","7-12 years","8-10 years","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The term backward class implies backwardness","choices":["Socially & educationally","Economically","Culturally","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Backward classes commission is appointed by the","choices":["Prime Minister","President","Governor","Chief Minister of all states"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Types of emergencies provided in the Indian Constitution is","choices":["4","5","6","3"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"The power to declare emergency is vested in the","choices":["Prime Minister","President","Governor","Chief Minister"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"National Emergency may be declared on the ground of","choices":["Internal disturbance","Political instability","War","Natural calamities"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"National Emergency may be declared on ____grounds","choices":["5","2","6","3"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"National Emergency may be declared under the following Article","choices":["360","2","352","375"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"National emergency can be declared when the cabinet communicates to the president","choices":["Orally","In writing","Either orally or in writing","None of these"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Proclamation of emergency must be laid before","choices":["Both the Houses of the Parliament","Either House of the Parliament","Before the supreme court","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Proclamation of emergency must be approved within","choices":["2 months","1 Month","6 Months","1 year"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"A resolution approving the proclamation must be passed by","choices":["Simple majority","Special Majority","Either special or simple majority","None of these"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Once approved, proclamation of emergency remains in force for","choices":["1 Year","6 Years","6 months","3 months"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Proclamation of emergency may be varied or cancelled by the","choices":["Lok sabha","Rajya Sabha","Supreme Court","President"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"Proclamation of emergency at the first instance remains in force for","choices":["6 months","1 month","3 months","2 months"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"During Emergency the states can be given directions by the","choices":["Supreme Court","Centre","Parliament","None of these"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"During emergency, there is automatic suspension of rights guaranteed under","choices":["Article 14","Article 21","Article 19","Article 18"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"President can suspend the enforcement of fundamental Rights except","choices":["Articl2 14 & 19","Article 18 & 20","Article 21 & 22","Article 20 & 21"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"So far National Emergency has been declared____ times in India","choices":["Five","Six","Three","One"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"State emergency is also called as","choices":["Presidents rule","Prime Minister Rule","Governors Rule","Chief Justice Rule"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"State Emergency can be declared when there is","choices":["War","Failure of Constitutional machinery in states","Financial Crisis","None of these"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"President can impose State emergency when he receives a report from the","choices":["Chief Minister","Governor","Chief Justice","Attorney General"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"During State Emergency the President exercises the power of the","choices":["Chief Minister","Prime Minister","Governor","Chief Justice"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Financial Emergency may be declared when there is ________","choices":["Financial instability","War","Internal disturbance","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The duration of financial emergency is _______","choices":["6 months","2 months","3 months","1 year"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Federal constitutions means a constitution in which powers are divided between the___","choices":["Central & state","States only","People & States","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The new ground of emergency added in 1978 to Article 352 was____","choices":["War","External Aggression","Armed Rebellion","Internal Disturbance"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"The powers to superintendent, direct & control elections is vested in the______","choices":["Planning commission","Finance Commission","Election Commission","None of these"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Election commission is _____ member commission","choices":["Single","Double","Multi","Four"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"The conditions of services of the election commissioners may be determined by the___","choices":["Prime Minister","Governor","President","Chief Justice of India"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"The removal of Chief Election Commissioner may be on grounds similar to that of ____","choices":["Judge of a High Court","Judge of the Supreme Court","Attorney General of India","Governor of a State"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Election Commissioners are appointed by the____","choices":["Chief Justice of India","Prime Minister","President","None of these"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Every citizen of the age of ____ years is eligible to vote in an election","choices":["21 years","16years","25 years","18 years"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"No. of rolls in a territorial constituency shall be ___","choices":["Two","One","Three","Unlimited"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Seats are reserved in favour of ___","choices":["SC & ST","Aged persons","Sick persons","Disabled persons"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"No. of seats to be reserved for Anglo Indian community in Lok Sabha is ___","choices":["Three","Two","One","Unlimited"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"The term of office of Election Commissioner is ___","choices":["1 Year","2 years","5 years","6 years"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"The members of the Anglo Indian community are nominated by the ____","choices":["Chief Minister","Prime Minister","President","Chief Justice of India"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"___ no. of days are allowed to file nomination","choices":["7 days","8 days","30 days","15 days"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"No. of days allowed to withdraw nomination papers is ___","choices":["1 day","3 days","2 days","15 days"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"No. of days allowed for campaigning","choices":["10 days","30 days","15 days","20 days"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"Election disputes can be adjudicated only by____","choices":["High Court","Criminal Court","Election Commission","Civil Court"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"Constitutions are classified into ____","choices":["Rigid","flexible","Rigid & flexible","None of these"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"The method of amending rigid constitution is by ___","choices":["Simple majority","Special majority","Cannot be amended","None of these"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Procedure to amend the constitution is contained in____","choices":["Article 268","Article 368","Article 338","None of these"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"No. of methods of amending the constitution ____","choices":["Two","One","Three","Four"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Consent by states for amending the constitution is known as ____","choices":["Resignation","Ratification","Registration","None of these"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"42nd Amendment Act came into force in","choices":["1956","1960","1976","1978"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"The words added to the preamble by 42nd amendment were","choices":["Socialist only","Secular only","Integrity only","All of these"],"correctAnswer":3},{"question":"Which among the following were given supremacy over fundamental rights.","choices":["Fundamental duties","Citizenship","DPSP","None of these"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Life of Lokha Sabha was increased from 5 to ___ years","choices":["6 years","7 years","9 years","10 years"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"44th Constitutional Amendment Act came into force in ___","choices":["1972","1976","1978","1980"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"____ was restored to 5 years","choices":["Life of Rajya Sabha","Life of Lok Sabha","Life of Both","None of these"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"73rd Amendment Act 1993 recognised the importance of____","choices":["Water Commission","Local Self Govt.","Central Govt.","State Govt."],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Establishment of ____ was the subject matter of 74th Amendment Act.","choices":["Corporations","Municipalities","High Court","None of these"],"correctAnswer":1},{"question":"Reservation in promotion to SC �s & STs is permitted _____","choices":["Article 16","Article 15 (4)","Article 16 (4-A)","None of these"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Article 21 (A) was a gift of ____ Amendment Act.","choices":["81st","82nd ","86th ","89th "],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"Right to education under Article 21 (A) is now a ____","choices":["Legal right","Constitutional Right","Fundamental Right","None of these"],"correctAnswer":2},{"question":"91st Amendment Act 2003 strengthens_____","choices":["Anti-defection Law","Preventive Detection Law","Ordinary property Law","None of these"],"correctAnswer":0},{"question":"The total no. of council of ministers including the Prime Minister should not exceed ____","choices":["10%","20%","15%","30%"],"correctAnswer":2}]